<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: rant | ]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.natescottwest.com/blog/categories/rant/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.natescottwest.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-21T12:28:25-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.natescottwest.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nate West]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Six Things The 'Education' System is Stupid Not to Do: A Brief Rant]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.natescottwest.com/blog/2013/06/21/six-things-the-education-system-is-stupid-not-to-do-a-brief-rant/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-21T09:49:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.natescottwest.com/blog/2013/06/21/six-things-the-education-system-is-stupid-not-to-do-a-brief-rant</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Some Background</h2>

<p>This all started when someone posting a link to some article about university students cheating to get by. They captioned it with “What do you think we can do to prevent cheating”. I thought it was the wrong question and that spawned this poorly written rant. Enjoy.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>The Rant</h2>

<p><strong>The Question</strong>: &ldquo;What can we do to prevent cheating&rdquo;</p>

<p><strong>The Answer</strong>:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Untie the teachers hands. Stop determining their usefulness based on their students grades. Grading systems are so easy to game, either by the students or the teachers. Too often we just end up punishing good teachers because their kids aren’t regurgitators and rewarding teachers who are dishonest or don’t challenge their students enough but manage to teach them how to consume, regurgitate, forget.</p></li>
<li><p>Stop rewarding information regurgitation with good grades. In fact, throw away grades all together. Let progress be it’s own reward and don’t force kids to progress until they’re ready. Likewise, let kids who are excelling progress the moment their ready and not a moment too late. Otherwise, you’ll just bore them and waste their time and yours.</p></li>
<li><p>Quizes, short answer/multiple choice/fill-in the blank test, worksheet style homework, etc. need to DIE. DIE. DIE. They promote regurgitation followed by amnesia like a night of binge drinking.</p></li>
<li><p>Cut the bullshit, busywork “homework”. Instead, assign reading assignments, videos to watch, information to google, etc. as homework. Better yet, make no assignments. If you actually engage students you ought to spark some interest in some topic in them that they will spend hours of their free time practicing or trying to learn more about.</p></li>
<li><p>In class, students should be working together to apply knowledge to real world problems while they’re in an environment where they can collaborate with others and learn from each other. Create rubrics and try to quantify and measure results… In your rubric, leave room for being surprised by a creative solution. Finding solutions no one thought of is called innovation.</p></li>
<li><p>Incentivize high performance with tangible rewards, praise, and recognition.If at all possible, let the solution to the problem be a reward in itself. Grades are imaginary numbers that kids are punished with. If you must use a number system, give positive numbers for doing well rather than penalizing for not doing as well as expecting. Reward is more effective than punishment. When you punish, you’re asking kids to try to avoid pain (cheat).</p></li>
<li><p>For as long as grades are the focus of school and not learning, intelligent kids are going to cheat. They should cheat in school. They’d be stupid to let themselves suffer because they aren’t willing to binge and purge information. I’ve never met an all A student who wasn’t a cheater, at least on occasion, when it came to homework and tests. Kids don’t even see it as cheating because they’re avoiding pain (your brain is wired to do that donchaknow).</p></li>
</ol>


<p><strong>The problem is not the cheating. Cheating is just a symptom of the un-innovative, unimaginative, brain cell killing, waste of time and money we’re calling “education” in the western world.</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
